ALI LARA

alilarag@mail.com • (614) 440-6494 • aliglara @ Linkedin • Austin, TX

SUMMARY

Analytical mindset, having extensive experience extracting useful facts from data. Enjoy open-ended issues and the application of developing technologies to challenging cases in various sectors—good communicator with an optimistic outlook and a desire to solve problems.

EXPERIENCE

Process Assistant, Amazon, Austin, TX

Mar 2023 - present

- Supervised a 35-member team aimed at developing an effective inbound workflow for processing 70k+ packages daily
- Streamlined the implemented workflow to reduce setup and processing time in a safe environment
- Assessed and developed production and labor plans
- Adapted team resources based on statistical real-time manufacturing metrics
- Collaborated with the leadership team in performing a continuous evaluation of work methods, procedures, and policies
- Tracked performance and supported any identified retraining opportunities for T1-associates

Yard Marshal, Amazon, Columbus, OH

Dec 2021 - Mar 2023

- Coordinated with carriers to ensure timely and accurate delivery of goods to customers
- Handled dispatching duties and managed shipment tracking
- Maintained digital records of 20+ inbound and outbound line hauls daily
- Assisted in carrier contract negotiations and compliance
- Monitored Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) and reported results to management
- Authored an Excel-based tracking tool to reduce process defects by 75%
- Partnered with a 15-member team aimed at developing an efficient loading/unloading system for 40k+ packages daily
- Monitored adherence to the established training programs to ensure standard work in a safe environment

FC Associate, Amazon, Columbus, OH

Nov 2020 - Dec 2021

- Sought ongoing skill development on under-performing associates to meet production goals
- Outperformed KPIs designed for tracking T1-associates performance: 379 UPH, 500+ average stow rate, which represented being at the 95th percentile
- Classified hazardous residues following federal and local EPA/RCRA standards for handling, disposal, or shipping
- Used technical knowledge to troubleshoot any issues related to damaged packages, processing hazmats, returns, and third-party contractor shipping
- Assisted to learning coordinator in coaching Day-1 and Week-1 associates in standards of work and safety culture

Machine Learning Engineer II, MCL Control, Venezuela

May 2012 - Sep 2019

- Shaped machine learning algorithms to develop predictive models and optimize the performance of advanced control algorithms for industrial processes
- Assisted researchers team in engineering a standard workflow for implementing non-parametric statistical models in oil/gas processes
- Engineered neural network models in Python/Tensorflow to estimate physical parameters required by process simulations to improve the application performance
- Mentored 10+ junior engineers over one year on using XGBoost and random forest models to optimize the feature selection for machine learning projects
- Gathered information, identified analytical requirements, and developed data-driven based models to translate complex business needs into actionable analytic projects

Researcher, Universidad Central of Venezuela, Venezuela

Mar 2005 - Nov 2020

- Researched chemical reaction engineering, mathematical modeling, simulation and optimization, process synthesis
 and design, including economic assessments, process integration, and machine learning techniques for industrial
 process evaluation
- Lectured in several chemical engineering areas, including thermodynamics, chemical reactor design, numerical methods, industrial process simulation, and statistical modeling

- Proposed a problem-solved learning experience in different subjects following the ABET guidance.
- Coached 200+ chemical engineering undergraduates with regards to academic pathways and toward degree completion and established and provided career counseling for a network of cooperatives, internships, and externships to foster academic to-industry pipeline

PROJECTS

- Design of an industrial plant for solar hydrogen production by water splitting 2020
- Develop a semi-automatic tool for HAZOP nodes detection from industrial process P&IDs 2020
- An assistive tool to perform HAZOP studies based on autoregressive models and machine learning techniques in compliance with design specifications 2020
- Prediction of turbo-compressors performance degradation using deep learning techniques 2019

EDUCATION

Correlation One - Amazon, Data Analytics BootCamp	2022
DataCamp.com, Python for Data Scientist	2017
Universidad Central of Venezuela, M.Sc. Chemical Engineering	2005 – 2008
Universidad Central of Venezuela, B.Sc. Chemical Engineering	1990 – 1998

SKILLS

- Process modeling: Statistical modeling, Matlab, Hysys
- Data Analysis: Excel, SQL, NoSQL, Tableau
- Machine learning: Python, R, TensorFlow